Let's open up to page נג ע"ב Nun Gimmel Amud Bet and
start the beginning of a new
פרק. Perek. We're really not going to look at the issues of
the משנה. Mishnah. We're going to use the משנה Mishnah as a
jumping off point for a couple of pages of אגדתא, Aggadeta, so
it'll be a fun few days. The משנה Mishnah had spoken about
כיצד מעברין, Keitzad Me'abrin, not to be confused with מערבין, Me'arvin, עירוב.
Eiruv. מעברין Me'abrin like עיבור, Ibbur, pregnant woman, because it talks about,
you know, basically making the lines around the city so you get
extra space. You sort of, the city juts out more than it
normally would because any protrusion you square off and you get extra
space. So that's going to be the jumping off point of the
גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara three lines
from the top on נג עמוד א. Nun Gimmel Amud Alef.
רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, the בית Beit of רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel.
חד תני מעברין, Chad tani Me'abrin, one has the version of the
משנה Mishnah with an עין, Ayin, עיבור, Ibbur, pregnant, וחד תני מעברין
ve'chad tani Me'avrin with an אלף. Alef. מאן דתני מעברין, Man de'tani
Me'avrin, so the one that says מעברין, Me'avrin, איבר איבר, eiver eiver,
like you add limbs. Okay? So again, you extend it by adding
limbs. ומאן דתני מעברין כאישה עוברה, U'man de'tani Me'abrin ke'ishah ubarah, like
a pregnant woman. So difference between an אלף Alef and an עין.
Ayin. מערת
המכפלה, Me'arat HaMachpelah, it's interesting by the way I should just say
that there's other גמרות Gemarot that indicate that in more Greek cities
in Israel, Greek-Roman cities, they weren't able to distinguish between עין Ayin
and אלף, Alef, and that has really indicates the lack of the
guttural ability to speak a Semitic and guttural language. So it is
interesting here that a question of an עין Ayin and an אלף
Alef would actually be pronounced differently and in an oral culture you
would think you would tell the difference, but the גמרא Gemara elsewhere
does reflect the sort of loss of guttural vowels.
Yes, they were the first אשכנזים. Ashkenazim.
First אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has other
debates of רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel about certain interpretations. מערת המכפלה, Me'arat
HaMachpelah, what does it mean by the double cave? רב ושמואל, Rav
u'Shmuel, חד אמר שני בתים זה לפנים מזה, chad amar shenei batim
zeh lifnim mizeh, double is two houses, one inside of the other.
So it's like a cave that there's an outer chamber and then
an inner chamber, maybe a chamber behind it. That's doubled. וחד אמר
בית על גביו, Ve'chad amar bayit al gabav, like it actually is
two stories. And that's the idea of doubled because a house is
normally defined by the roof in הלכה, Halachah, so it has two
roofs. בשלמא למאן דאמר זה על גב זה היינו מכפלה, Bishlama le'man
de'amar zeh al gav zeh hainu Machpelah, which is what the גמרא
Gemara says. If it's one on top of the other, we understand
that's the meaning of the word מכפלה, Machpelah, that it's doubled. אלא
למאן דאמר שני בתים זה לפנים מזה מאי מכפלה? Ela le'man de'amar
shenei batim zeh lifnim mizeh mai Machpelah? What does מכפלה Machpelah mean?
Because again, it would not be considered doubled because it's only one
roof. So שכפולה בזוגות, she'kfulah b'zugot, it really, the doubling here does
not mean the chambers, so in the chambers thing wasn't really relevant,
it really means that it has multiple pairs of people buried there.
You know,
שרה ואברהם, Sarah ve'Avraham, and you know, and רחל ויצחק... Rachel ve'Yitzchak...
I mean רבקה
ויצחק... Rivkah ve'Yitzchak... רחל לאה ויעקב, Rachel Leah ve'Yaakov, רבקה ויצחק, Rivkah
ve'Yitzchak, etc. Okay, and also according to the גמרא, Gemara, אדם וחוה.
Adam ve'Chavah.
Not רחל? Rachel?
What? Not רחל, Rachel, I'm sorry. Right, רחל Rachel is not buried
there. There you go. Alright, good. Well said, well said.
It's early, it's early. Okay, anyway, good point.
The מהרש"א Maharsha points out that by the way there is a
problem just in terms of פשט הפסוקים pshat ha'pesukim because it says,
it calls it שדה המכפלה. S'deh HaMachpelah. So מכפלה Machpelah according to
the פשט הפסוקים pshat ha'pesukim seems to be referring more to the
name of the place than actually the configuration of the cave, unless
you say that the name of the field was named after the
cave.
Okay, now similarly קרית ארבע, Kiryat Arba, what does קרית ארבע Kiryat
Arba mean? So אמר רב יצחק, amar Rav Yitzchak, קרית הארבע. Kiryat
Ha'arba. What does קרית הארבע Kiryat Ha'arba mean? ארבע זוגות, Arba zugot,
אדם וחוה, אברהם ושרה, יצחק ורבקה, יעקב ולאה. Adam ve'Chavah, Avraham ve'Sarah,
Yitzchak ve'Rivkah, Yaakov ve'Leah. There you see, it's in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so that's what it means קרית ארבע, Kiryat Arba, that there
are four pairs that are there. The מהרש"א Maharsha says that it
really seems like in ספר יהושע Sefer Yehoshua that ארבע Arba is
the name of the person, but he says that the, in one
place in בראשית Bereishit it says קרית הארבע, Kiryat Ha'arba, which is,
and הארבע Ha'arba you would not use a ה' הידיעה Heh ha'yedi'ah
if it was a proper name. So that's really the דרשה drasha
of the גמרא. Gemara. ויהי בימי אמרפל, Vayehi bimei Amraphel, now back
to רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. It was in the days of
אמרפל, Amraphel, מלך שנער. Melech Shinar. And the מדרש Midrash associates אמרפל
Amraphel with נמרוד, Nimrod, because it says by נמרוד, Nimrod, הוא היה
גבור ציד לפני ה', hu hayah gibor tziyad lifnei Hashem, and the
first major war we find in the תורה Torah is with אמרפל.
Amraphel. So there's an identification of אמרפל Amraphel and נמרוד. Nimrod. So,
now we're going to have a debate of רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel.
רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, חד אמר נמרוד שמו, chad amar Nimrod sh'mo,
his proper name was נמרוד, Nimrod, and אמרפל Amraphel was more a
descriptive name. ולמה נקרא שמו אמרפל? Ve'lamah nikrah sh'mo Amraphel? שאמר, she'amar,
פל, pal, right? אמר ופיל... Amar ve'hipil... אמר ופיל Amar ve'hipil לאברהם
אבינו בתוך כבשן האש. le'Avraham Avinu b'toch kivshan ha'esh. So the famous
מדרש Midrash that נמרוד Nimrod was, you know, sort of gave אברהם
Avraham an ultimatum, you know, either to give up his monotheism or
be cast into the fire, and he was cast into the fire.
That's אמר ופיל. amar ve'hipil. So he was the one that did
that. וחד
אמר אמרפל שמו, Ve'chad amar Amraphel sh'mo, no, אמרפל Amraphel is his
proper name.
ולמה נקרא שמו נמרוד? Ve'lamah nikrah sh'mo Nimrod? שהמריד את כל העולם.
She'himrid et kol ha'olam. כולו עליו במלכותו kulo alav b'malchuto that he
basically got everybody to rebel against God. So and this is associating
it with probably him as the head
of the whole insurrection about מגדל בבל, Migdal Bavel, right? Because it's
מלך שנער, Melech Shinar, so it's the same basic location and so
on. So he was the one, he was the mastermind, the leader
behind that.
I should note that that the מערת המכפלה, Ma'arat HaMachpelah, that's simply
a דרש. drash. The context of the פרשה parsha makes it clear
המכפלה HaMachpelah was simply a name of a place.
I said that, I said it says, yeah, while you were getting
your חומש Chumash you weren't hearing that. But I pointed out that
the מהרש"א Maharsha already makes that point that it says שדי המכפלה,
S'dei HaMachpelah, so it's certainly a דרש, drash, right. Okay, so ויקם
מלך חדש על מצרים. Vayakom Melech Chadash Al Mitzrayim. Now, a lot
of these are famous because רש"י Rashi brings them down. Okay, so
a new king arose over Egypt. רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel, חד אמר
חדש ממש, chad amar chadash mamash, literally new, וחד אמר שנתחדשו גזירותיו.
v'chad amar she-nit-chadesh gezeirotav.
No, he changed his tune and he started making new edicts. מאן
דאמר חדש ממש, man d'amar chadash mamash, דכתיב חדש. d'chtiv chadash. I
mean what do you mean, the Torah says new? ומאן דאמר שנתחדשו
גזירותיו, u-man d'amar she-nit-chadesh gezeirotav, מן דלא כתיב וימת וימלוך, min d'lo
ktiv vayamot vayimloch,
because it doesn't say that the previous king died, it says just
a new king arose. ולמאן דאמר שנתחדשו גזירותיו, u-l'man d'amar she-nit-chadesh gezeirotav,
הא כתיב אשר לא ידע את יוסף? ha ktiv asher lo yada
et Yosef? But it says he didn't know יוסף. Yosef. So obviously
if he was the same old guy of course he knew יוסף.
Yosef. So no, מאי אשר לא ידע את יוסף? mai asher lo
yada et Yosef? דהוה דמי כמאן דלא ידעה ליה ליוסף כלל. d'havi
dami k'man d'lo yadeh leh l'Yosef klal. He made it, he acted
in ways which were as if he did not know who יוסף
Yosef was. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, י"ח ימים גידלתי אצל רבי הושעיא. Yud-Chet yamim gidalti etzel
Rabbi Oshaya. Now
this is going to seem like a digression, but it's going to
circle back to the issue of מעברין m'avrin or מאברין m'avrin with
an ע ayin or an א. aleph. Okay, י"ח ימים גידלתי אצל
רבי הושעיא ברבי. Yud-Chet yamim gidalti etzel Rabbi Oshaya b'rebi.
I learned for eighteen days, not an enormous amount of time, but
eighteen days. And the funny by the way the use of the
verb
גידלתי.
gidalti.
Okay.
All right, so גידלתי gidalti which means I grew up, not I
spent eighteen years or I spent eighteen days, I grew up. You
don't grow up, you know, I don't know what that means exactly.
It's a funny verb. But anyway, I learned with רבי הושעיא. Rabbi
Oshaya. Now רבי הושעיא Rabbi Oshaya was roughly at the same period
of רבי, Rebi, he was as we see here a רבי Rebi
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the sort of their transition between
the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים. Amoraim. He also together with
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, right, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, thank you. He
together with רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, how'd you know what I was
going to say? He together with רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya were the
sort of editors of the
תוספתא, Tosefta, right. The גמרא Gemara says, you know, any ברייתא דלא
תני בי רבי הושעיא או בי רבי חייא, Baraita d'lo tani bei
Rabbi Oshaya o bei Rabbi Chiya, you know, you can't trust the
text because they were very, you know, establishing the clear text of
the ברייתות Baraitot and particularly of the תוספתא. Tosefta. So they sort
of did parallel work with the ברייתות Baraitot that רבי Rebi did
with the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, I
spent eighteen days by רבי הושעיא ברבי. Rabbi Oshaya b'rebi. ברבי B'rebi
is just an honorific, it means like an important person, the great
רבי הושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. ולא למדתי ממנו אלא דבר אחד במשנתנו, v'lo
limadti mimenu ela davar echad b'mishnatenu,
which is a pretty funny like, he says, I spent eighteen days
and I only learned from him one thing that relating to the
משנה. Mishnah. What was the one thing I learned from him? כיצד
מאברין את הערים באל"ף. keitzad m'avrin et ha-arim b'aleph.
Because he told me the משנה Mishnah מאברין m'avrin is with an
א. aleph. So it sounds like a pretty big put-down, right? I
only learned one thing from him and the one thing I learned
from him was pretty a trivial issue. It doesn't affect any הלכה
Halacha or anything. So you really wonder what the point of this
was. I mean, you know, but okay, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with this.
Maybe he went there because he wanted to, you know, confirm or
or reject certain questions he had. So he knew the right answers
to all of them except this one.
Right, I understand, but it's sort of but isn't it a little
bit dismissing the importance of רבי הושעיא? Rabbi Oshaya? I spent eighteen
days and only there was only one thing that he clarified for
me?
Maybe he learned a lot of other things but only one thing
relating to the משניות. mishnayot. Right, that could be. Okay, so but
you know, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this.
Now it is consistent by the way with רבי הושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya's
sort of enterprise of establishing the proper text of the תנאי Tannaic
material. So that's particularly, you know, so let's see, let's see how
the גמרא Gemara goes.
You'd say that of every academic, you spend years toiling away at
research and you find one thing. Ten years. Right, like footnote.
Like footnote.
Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, איני? ini? Is this really
true? ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, י"ב תלמידים היו לו לרבי
הושעיא ברבי. Yud-Bet talmidim hayu lo l'Rabbi Oshaya b'rebi. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said the same רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that there were
eighteen students, maybe eighteen, י"ב. twelve. I keep, I don't know what
I'm doing this morning. Anyway, eighteen days, twelve students. There were י"ב
twelve students, maybe twelve prize students that רבי הושעיא Rabbi Oshaya had.
י"ח ימים גידלתי ביניהם. Yud-Chet yamim gidalti beineihem. And I spent eighteen
days among them. ולמדתי לב כל אחד ואחד. v'limadti lev kol echad
v'echad. I understood the heart of each one of them. רש"י Rashi
sort of says that means like the you know their approach to
learning, their methodology, their way of thinking, וחכמת כל אחד ואחד Vechachmat
kol echad ve'echad and the wisdom of every one of them. So
רש"י Rashi says here wisdom sort of means you know their knowledge,
although חכמה chochma usually means more than just knowledge. But I understood
their whole you know way of thinking and their particular דרך derech
and their insight and what they knew.
So the
גמרא Gemara says... So how so you see he learned a lot
of things during those 18 days. He learned all these different approaches
and he learned what everybody there knew. So the גמרא Gemara says
no. גמרא Gemara says לב כל אחד ואחד וחכמת כל אחד ואחד
גמר. Lev kol echad ve'echad vechachmat kol echad ve'echad gemar. So he
learned their approaches, he learned their ways of thinking, but גמרא לא
גמר. Gemara lo gemar. He didn't actually learn any new material. Okay?
So anyway, if you think about it like what I think learning
a methodology is more important than learning material, right? What is it?
Give me a fish feed me for a day, teach me to
fish feed me for life. But okay, but now the גמרא Gemara
is starting to qualify. Fine, he learned their way of thinking, but
he didn't learn any new material. אי בעית אימא, Iba'it eima, if
you want I could say, מנייהו דידהו גמר, Mineihu dideihu gemar, he
learned from the students. מניה דידיה לא גמר, Minei didei lo gemar,
he didn't learn anything new from רבי אושעיא. Rebbi Oshaya. Again which
is like okay that's pretty fascinating. ואי בעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, and
if you want and here's really
what you know what it seems to be saying, what was suggested,
דבר אחד במשנתנו גמר. Davar echad bemishnateinu gemar. He only learned one
new thing about the משנה. Mishna. Maybe he learned a lot of
other things, but relating to the משנה, Mishna, there was only one
thing that רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya helped him clarify.
Okay. ואמר רבי יוחנן כשהיינו לומדים תורה אצל רבי אושעיא. Ve'amar Rebbi
Yochanan keshehayinu lomdim Torah etzel Rebbi Oshaya. So רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
also said when we were learning תורה Torah by רבי אושעיא, Rebbi
Oshaya, היינו יושבים ארבע ארבע באמה, Hayinu yoshvim arba arba be'ama, four
of us would squeeze into one אמה. ama. If you think about
it that's pretty tight fit. If right if an אמה ama is
like a foot and a half. Maybe it means an אמה ama
by an אמה ama you know but still like it's a very
tight fit. So רש"י Rashi says everybody was crowding around him to
hear what he had to say. Of course that means he had
more than 12 students because if you have to crowd around and
squeeze in that tight, so maybe it was 12 prime students, prize
students.
Okay.
אמר רבי, Amar Rebbi, and רבי Rebbi said, כשהיינו לומדים תורה אצל
רבי אלעזר בן שמוע, Keshehayinu lomdim Torah etzel Rebbi Elazar ben Shamua,
when we were learning תורה Torah by רבי אלעזר בן שמוע, Rebbi
Elazar ben Shamua, so
that's סתם רב אלעזר, stam Rav Elazar, the תלמיד talmid of רבי
עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. He had five prize תלמידים, talmidim, right? רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir,
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, etc. One of them is רבי אלעזר. Rebbi
Elazar. So when we were learning תורה Torah by
רבי אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, היינו יושבים ששה ששה באמה. Hayinu yoshvim shisha
shisha be'ama. We would squeeze six of us into one אמה. ama.
Again which המהרש"א haMaharsha basically says it's either נס nes or exaggeration.
All right. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rebbi Yochanan. So continuing with this
idea of speaking about you know the sort of what it meant
to be learning by these previous master you know
גדולים, gedolim, so we continue with that theme. Although it is funny
because again so far what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan has said has
not you know sort of made us be overly impressive, even but
the גמרא Gemara clarified at least qualified it somewhat. Anyway but now
let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן רבי אושעיא ברבי בדורו, Amar
Rebbi Yochanan Rebbi Oshaya berabbi bedoro, רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya the great
one, right, in his generation, כרבי מאיר בדורו kerebbi Meir bedoro was
as great as רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was in his generation, which
was you know a generation earlier. מה רבי מאיר בדורו לא יכלו
חבריו לעמוד על סוף דעתו, Ma Rebbi Meir bedoro lo yachlu chaveirav
la'amod al sof da'ato, if you remember we had a lot of
אגדתא agadata before how רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was so brilliant, nobody
could figure out what he was saying. Okay? So he you know
he might have come to brilliant conclusions but nobody else could get
there. אף רבי אושעיא לא יכלו חבריו לעמוד על סוף דעתו. Af
Rebbi Oshaya lo yachlu chaveirav la'amod al sof da'ato. The same is
true by רבי אושעיא. Rebbi Oshaya. So maybe that's what רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan means that לא למדתי. lo lamadti. All I was able
to learn from him was some textual correction because maybe more of
the analysis that was beyond my reach. You know? So again it
is funny holding those two statements up side by side. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rebbi Yochanan, and now we're going to actually get into
a classic גמרא Gemara that compares earlier generations to later ones. לבן
של ראשונים כפתחו של אולם. Liban shel rishonim kepitcho shel ulam. The
heart, meaning the understanding of the earlier generations, was like the opening
of the אולם, ulam, right, the sort of the hall before the
היכל, heichal, right, the קודש הקדשים, kodesh hakadashim, the קודש. kodesh. ושל
אחרונים כפתחו של היכל. Veshel acharonim kepitcho shel heichal. The later ones
was like the opening of the היכל heichal and this goes back
to the very first פרק perek if you remember the אולם ulam
was 20 אמות amot wide and the היכל heichal was only 10
אמות amot wide. So this is reflecting this sort of theology or
this approach of you know ירידת הדורות. yeridat hadorot. That as the
generations continue, their depth of understanding you know you know gets more
and more limited.
Using that
metaphor they're also closer to the heart of the matter, the אחרונים.
acharonim.
Oh, because as you... that's an interesting question. Oh, you know what,
that's brilliant because you know there's always this issue, I mean that's...
who was the first one that said, I think I don't think
they know who the first one that said about you know about
the midgets standing on the shoulders of giants, right? Why is it
that you know later generations can make advances that earlier ones cannot?
And it's not because they were necessarily greater in wisdom or understanding,
but they're like midgets standing on the shoulders of giants. the giants
preceded them, they add a little bit, so they can see further
than the giants were able to see. So, you know, maybe that's,
I didn't think about that, but maybe it's saying, you know, we
have less understanding but we're building on what the previous generation did
so we're getting a little bit closer. I don't know if that's
פשט pshat or not but it's a beautiful thought.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, ואנו, v'anu, but now
it doesn't work with the third part of this. ואנו כמלא נקב
מחט סידקית, v'anu kemale nekev machat sidkit, and we, our understanding is
only like the opening of a very thin needle. So as opposed
to ten אמות, amos, you know, our understanding is like that, our
ability to see through and to get through the matter.
So where the גמרא Gemara say, אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva,
now who were the early ones, who were these generations you're referring
to? ראשונים, Rishonim, the early generations, is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אחרונים
Achronim is רבי אלעזר בן שמוע, Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua, which is
רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, the student of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the
רבי Rebbe of רבי Rebbe as we just heard a minute ago.
And those are the generations, and then anyone after that from רבי
Rebbe down, it's all you know you know, it's all downhill from
there. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, some say ראשונים Rishonim רבי אלעזר בן
שמוע. Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua. No, no, no. Actually the early generations
even by רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva תלמידים, talmidim,
they already had this broad understanding. אחרונים, Achronim, when did it start
going downhill? That was רבי אושעיא ברבי. Rabbi Oshaya b'Rebbe. But either
way, then you get to my generation, because it's רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan talking. ואנו כמלא נקב מחט סידקית. v'anu kemale nekev machat sidkit.
We, now the generation of the אמוראים Amoraim as compared to the
תנאים, Tannaim, it's a much greater drop-off, right? Because part of also
what it might be referring to is that line between תנאים Tannaim
and אמוראים. Amoraim. Right? So the first one sort of, you know,
the big drop-off happened after רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which was sort
of going to רבי. Rebbe. רבי Rebbe was not fully transitional, but
he was like the end of the period. The next version, the
drop-off is the line between the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים. Amoraim.
So it might also be coming to explain, you know, the built-in
assumption of the גמרא Gemara is that, you know, an אמורא Amora
cannot argue on a תנא. Tanna. You can explain a תנא, Tanna,
you can't argue. The only question is that transitional generation of רב
Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan where the גמרא Gemara says like
רב תנא הוא ופליג. Rav Tanna hu palig. But basically, if you're
clearly out of the תנאים, Tannaim, you can't argue. Why not? Right?
Why? What's the big difference between, you know, that generation and this
generation? So some of it might be based on this assumption about
this big drop-off in terms of, you know, understanding and so on
that's reflected here. So I should say something about this whole ירידת
הדורות Yeridas Hadoros approach, which is here and like I said maybe
even sort of specifically around the transition of תנאים Tannaim to אמוראים
Amoraim as an explanation of the difference. There's a lovely book out
by Menachem Kellner called Maimonides and the Descent of Generations. Small little
book, like 50 pages or something, 100 pages. Anyway, and what he
basically shows is that this idea of ירידת הדורות, Yeridas Hadoros, while
certainly an approach that has its basis in גמרא, Gemara, there's other
גמרות Gemaras that say like, you know, אם ראשונים כמלאכים, Im rishonim
kemalachim, then you know,
אנחנו כבני אדם. anachnu kivnei adam. אם ראשונים כבני אדם, Im rishonim
kivnei adam, אנחנו כחמורים, anachnu kachamorim, and not like the חמור chamor
of פנחס בן יאיר. Pinchas ben Yair. You know, so it makes
these radical differences between how their greatness and how and how meager
we are, and how lowly we are. So certainly there are גמרות
Gemaras that say that, but there are other גמרות Gemaras that don't
reflect that idea, you know, and speak about for example, I mean
just one idea, הלכה כבתראי, halacha k'basrai, you go by the later
generations because it reflects the idea now might be sort of like
the midgets on the shoulders of giants, that it reflects the fact
that they're building on previous generations and they have the ability to
see previous generations. But he says particularly in רמב"ם. Rambam. In רמב"ם
Rambam you see in a lot of places the רמב"ם Rambam understood
that you know understanding and science advances, that later generations understand better
in terms of science, in terms of medicine, in terms of, you
know, astronomy, all these types of issues. So he basically, you know,
says that this issue first of all it's not like it's תורה
משה מסיני, Torah Moshe miSinai, this idea of ירידת הדורות, Yeridas Hadoros,
and number two it's a question about its use in terms of
explaining the authority of חז"ל. Chazal. How much do we believe that
the authority of חז"ל Chazal rests upon the idea that they were
smarter than us and they knew everything and we don't know anything?
Right? For some people that's very important. And because of that you
can't suggest that they ever made a mistake because that undermines that
sense of their authority, because the only reason they're authoritative is they
know everything and we know nothing. But he says but according to
רמב"ם, Rambam, the authority of the גמרא Gemara is not based on
the fact that they knew better than us, it's based on the
fact that it was canonized, that it was accepted by כלל ישראל.
Klal Yisrael. And that's why the בבלי Bavli is more authoritative than
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, not because the בבלי Bavli knew better but the
בבלי Bavli was what was canonized and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi wasn't. And
the כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh says the same thing is true about
this issue of אמורא Amora not arguing on תנאים Tannaim or ראשונים
Rishonim not arguing on אמוראים. Amoraim. Right? Where's that from? He says
it's not all it's from is from an implicit sort of, you
know, consensus canonization of the later generation. Basically the משנה Mishnah came
out and after everybody after the משנה Mishnah implicitly accepted the authority
of the משנה Mishnah and canonized the משנה Mishnah or canonized the
תנאי Tannaitic material and therefore it was through that. the act of
canonization through the people essentially that it was invested with the weight
and the authority that it has. So you know, so that's a
very different approach to the nature of rabbinic authority. It does not
demand insisting that you know they knew everything and we know nothing.
So the issues around here are really very deep in terms of
a general you know question about rabbinic authority and attitude towards חזל
Chazal and all those types of issues if you have to believe
you know that they can't make any mistakes and you know and
we know nothing and so on.
Yes, a similar issue with ראשונים Rishonim versus אחרונים. Acharonim.
Right, exactly. It continues on and why does the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch become largely authoritative? What,
did משה Moshe come down from סיני Sinai with the שולחן ערוך?
Shulchan Aruch? You know, so again, according to the canonization approach, it's
because you know over time, it didn't happen immediately, but more and
more it became the ספר Sefer that people referred to for various
reasons, which I could you know, A: that it was very well
organized and short and to the point; B: that when רב יוסף
קארו Rav Yosef Karo wrote it, he says explicitly he's not just
writing his own personal opinion, he's trying to present a consensus opinion,
so that gave it greater weight because it was presented as a
consensus opinion. Anyway, so over time people kept on using it and
the more and more you refer to it and use it, the
more it becomes somewhat canonical. Right? Like nowadays, tell somebody that it's
possible to פסקן Pasken against the משנה ברורה, Mishnah Berurah, they'll think
you're an אפיקורוס, Apikores, you know, but whoever said the משנה ברורה
Mishnah Berurah was authoritative? It's because once things become very accessible and
usable and everybody refers to it, that is a way of it
becoming invested with authority. Those that adopt the other approach that the
authority comes from the fact that it's like true and you know
and the people and whatever and the חזל Chazal knew everything and
we know nothing, so why is the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch authoritative?
So actually some אחרונים Acharonim say that they do use the reality
of sort of historical canonization, but in an indirect way. They say,
let's see if you can finish this sentence: the fact that the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch has been accepted by כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
is a proof that what? That's right.
It's רצון השם, Ratzon Hashem, it's סייעתא דשמיא Siyata D'shmaya that God
would not have allowed it to be accepted by כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael if it did not embody the true הלכה, Halacha, you know,
the true הלכה. Halacha. So there are these very two different approaches
to where you see halakhic authority coming from. Anyway, so that is
I think particularly here also where he speaks about the drop-off between
תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים.
Amoraim. Versus question about
for example, if I understand correctly, מאירי, Meiri, you know, which
was discovered later as it were, right? Or was not...
What was? מאירי. Meiri. מאירי, Meiri, right, absolutely.
Absolutely. The חזון איש Chazon Ish was very much of this canonization
approach, and the חזון איש Chazon Ish said that the ראשונים Rishonim
that are discovered that were not part of the מסורה Mesorah of
כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael have no halakhic weight. Not because he didn't
think that they might not have been smart or they might not
have had a better פשט Peshat in the גמרא, Gemara, but what
gives things halakhic weight is their acceptance within to the halakhic system.
Now the question becomes that that's an evolving reality, right? The same
way the משנה ברורה, Mishnah Berurah, you know, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch became accepted, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah did, you know, when
more and more people start referencing the מאירי Meiri or referencing whatever
they're referencing and it becomes more and more used by פוסקים, Poskim,
then it can start to be given that weight, you know? But
yes, that exact idea, the חזון איש Chazon Ish very much was
you know of that approach. Also questions how you deal with manuscript
error and all these types of questions.
He says that God wanted it...
Right. Yes, right. So there's a lot of important sort of theological
issues that underpins all of this.
Or even better, the censorship. Right.
Okay, so let's continue. So גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, where
are we? So we went to the who refers to. אמר אביי:
Amar Abaye: ואנן. Va'anan. So that was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan talking.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was at least you know the generation after
you know the first generation of אמוראים. Amoraim. We, אביי Abaye towards
the end of the אמוראים, Amoraim, he says: כסיכתא בגודא לגמרא. Kesikhtsa
beguda legemara. We are like trying to get a peg to go
into a stone wall when it comes to גמרא. Gemara. Now גמרא
Gemara here might mean, גמרא Gemara is sort of tradition in the
sense of
of like because part of the question is there's always two issues
in the גמרא. Gemara. One is the passing down of the information,
especially in an oral culture, so it's learning everything that you had
you know you know learning the מסורה. Mesorah. The other is using
your סברא. Svara. So אביי Abaye is particularly saying, you know, it's
like look everything else, even the needle the hole went all the
way through, right? It might be less. Here you're trying to push
a peg into a wall and it still doesn't get to go
through. Maybe you get it to go in a little bit like
a nail into a wall, but it's not going all the way
through. And but he says בגמרא. Begemara. Now obviously the further the
generations are removed, maybe there is like less of a clear chain
of transmission and some of the material is lost. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, now רבא Rava says: ואנן כאצבעתא בקירא לסברא. Va'anan ke'etsbata bekira
lisvara. Now this is something that's different because this is not just...
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now רבא Rava says ואנן כאצבעא בבירא לסברא.
ve-anan ke-etzbe'a be-bira le-sevara. Now this is something that's different because this
is not just the passing on of information, but it's the analytical
ability. We are like a finger in wax when it comes to
סברא. sevara. Now if you put a finger in like dried wax,
you know, it doesn't work, or maybe if you put it in
soft wax, but then you remove it, it again it doesn't go
too far or it sort of closes up depending on how how
soft or liquefied the wax is.
I was sort of wondering, although I think it's obviously a misread,
if
רבא Rava maybe
you could use רבא's Rava metaphor to be something of the opposite.
Like סברא sevara we might not be as bad; like maybe the
line of tradition and, you know, some some information is lost. But,
you know, if you put a finger in wax, it'll actually stay
and make an impression, you know? So I don't know, but it
does still and it sticks a little. Yeah, or some of it
sticks, you get some of it. But still, it seems like רבא
Rava with the peg in the wax, it's not going all the
way through, yes. אביי Abaye and רבא Rava were after רבי יוחנן?
Rabbi Yochanan? Way after. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was first generation אמוראים,
Amoraim, and אביי Abaye and רבא Rava were close to the end
of the אמוראים. Amoraim. That's what I thought. Right. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, okay. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, אנן,
anan, אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi says אנן כאצבעא בבירא לשכחה.
anan ke-etzbe'a be-bira le-shikhcha. So we are like putting your finger into
a well when it comes to forgetting, meaning there's absolutely no resistance
to us to forget. We just in one ear out the other.
So again, a lot of this has to do with, you know,
retaining information. And of course as the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al
peh increases, there's more information to retain, right, you know the joke
about the kid whatever trying to study and memorize all the presidents,
and his mom said, 'When I was your age, I knew, you
know, all the presidents backwards and forwards.' He said, 'Well, yeah, there
were only two or three then.' So anyway,
okay, but anyway, but it's so so a lot of this גמרא
Gemara and שכחה shikhcha have to do with retaining information. It does
raise interesting questions in terms of analysis and insight. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב.
Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. So said אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. בני יהודה שהקפידו bnei Yehuda she-hikpido now we're going
to sort of circle back. That whole discussion was because of the
one thing רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan learned from רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
at least as far as משנה Mishna was concerned was מעברין m'abrin
with an אלף. aleph. Now we're going to have another story that
gets us back to מעברין m'abrin or מעברין. m'abrin. Let's take a
look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, בני
יהודה שהקפידו על לשונם, bnei Yehuda she-hikpido al leshonam, the בני יהודה
bnei Yehuda the people of Judea as opposed to גליל, Galil, right,
which is how ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was divided those at that
time, they were very careful, precise with their with their language. נתקיימה
תורתם בידם. nitkayma Toratam be-yadam. So their תורה Torah was established, they
held on to their תורה. Torah. בני גליל שלא הקפידו על לשונם,
bnei Galil she-lo hikpido al leshonam, בני גליל bnei Galil that maybe
spoke loosely, did not speak as refined, לא נתקיימה תורתם בידם, lo
nitkayma Toratam be-yadam, their תורה Torah was not as established. So the
גמרא Gemara says: מידי בכפידא תליא מילתא? Midi be-kfeida talya milta? I
don't understand. What does knowing your תורה, Torah, remembering your תורה Torah
have to do with how careful
you
are with your language? So the גמרא Gemara spells it out. אלא,
ela, here's what it means. בני יהודה דדייקי לישנא, bnei Yehuda de-dayki
lishana, בני יהודה bnei Yehuda are very exact in the language, meaning
if they learn a text, a משנה, Mishna, right, and again it's
all an oral culture, so that's key is how do you hold
on to the information. So they are very precise, they establish a
precise text, ומתני להו סימנא, u-matni lehu simana, and therefore they're able
to have like mnemonics in order to remember because you have an
exact text and you have a way of remembering. נתקיימה תורתם בידם,
nitkayma Toratam be-yadam, they're able therefore they they remember it very well.
בני גליל דלא דייקי לישנא, bnei Galil de-lo dayki lishana, בני גליל
bnei Galil that, you know, is not so careful about getting down
the exact text, ולא מתני להו סימנא, ve-lo matni lehu simana, so
if you don't have an exact text, everything is sort of a
moving target number one, and therefore it's very hard to make certain
mnemonics because you're not being so precise to remember. לא נתקיימה תורתם
בידם, lo nitkayma Toratam be-yadam, it did not get established. By the
way, רש"י Rashi also says is that it's not just establishing each
משנה, Mishna, but if you have a particular order and you're very
careful about the order of which משנה Mishna follows the other, you
can make a mnemonic to remind you, you know, about the order
of what the next one is, whereas if you're more disorganized, then,
you know, then you sort of lose a whole you lose the
whole thread, yes.
But רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi lived in the גליל Galil
and we're studying
the entire yeah, I don't I don't know what to to say
to that. Okay. Maybe when he got his memorizers to be from
בני יהודה, bnei Yehuda, not from בני גליל. bnei Galil. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to move on. בני גליל bnei
Galil so where were we? Okay. בני יהודה גמרו מחד רבא, bnei
Yehuda gamru mi-chad raba, again notice the word גמרא Gemara which is
learning and learning a text, right, which is very much like the
earlier discussion. They learned from only one teacher. נתקיימה תורתם בידם, nitkayma
Toratam be-yadam, so they held on to their תורה. Torah. בני גליל
דלא גמרו מחד רבא, bnei Galil de-lo gamru mi-chad raba, they learned
from all different teachers, לא נתקיימה תורתם בידם, lo nitkayma Toratam be-yadam,
they did not hold on to it. Now again, תוספות Tosafot makes
this point that this is about the information. If you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, דגמר מחד רבא לגמרא, de-gamar mi-chad raba le-Gemara, for like
the learning of, גמרא Gemara here means again of like material, passing
on of material, רב חד עדיף, rav chad adif, שלא יבלבלו לשונם
יחד, she-lo yevalbelu leshonam yachad, that, you know, you get one particular
version of the משנה, Mishna, you don't get every person you ask
gives you a different version of the משנה, Mishna, you get one
particular גירסא girsa and you learn it. אבל aval is a מצוה
*mitzvah*, but in terms of analysis, I mean in פרק קמא *Perek
Kama*, כל הלומד עבודה זרה *Kol halomed Avodah Zarah*, כל הלומד תורה
Torah לפני רב אחד אינו רואה סימן ברכה לעולם *Kol halomed Torah
lifnei rav echad eino roeh siman berachah le'olam*, right, so in order
to get different ways of analyzing methodology, thinking about things, you want
to expose yourself to a lot of different approaches and a lot
of different ways of thinking. But in order to learn the text,
you gotta learn—you gotta start with one text and then you can
work off of that. You know, חיים סולובייצ'יק *Chaim Soloveitchik* once made
an interesting point about how תוספות *Tosafot* was not possible until there
was a רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. Not because the תוספות *Tosafot* couldn't explain
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* did is he
established a default, a fixed meaning of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So,
you know, until then it was like a moving target. How do
you criticize, you know, how do you ask a critical question about
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* if you don't even—if you're not even sure
what—you know, if you have three possibilities what this line means? So
it's, you know, how do you start doing analysis? So once you
give a standard explanation, you've made it like a fixed target, then
you can do your analysis, and as a result of your analysis,
you can say, ah, really the answer is we have to give
a different explanation to the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, but as long as
there are multiple possibilities, you really can't get to the next stage.
So this is also the טענה *ta'anah*. You start with one text,
start with a clear, single version of a text from one רבי
rebbe *Rebbi*, then you can do your analysis. And then the analysis,
you're even—actually better if you expose yourself to more—to more approaches. Yes.
That makes learning ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* really difficult.
That's exactly why learning ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is difficult. How do you start
asking questions if you're—if you're like—it's like walking on, you know, on—on—quicksand,
you know, because you know that any question you ask, well maybe
I didn't understand this right, I have three possibilities what this could
mean, right? So yes, so that's exactly this, first establishing a text
even if it, you know, even if there's other texts out there,
other versions out there. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this: רבינא אמר amar, *Ravina amar*, בני יהודה Bnei Yehuda, דגלו מסכתא
masechta. *Bnei Yehuda degalu masechta*, בני יהודה Yehuda *Bnei Yehuda* that exposed
a מסכתא *masechta*, which what does that mean? רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
it means that they taught it to other people or—or some say
it means—or you know—or רש"י *Rashi* just says that—that they go in
depth, they reveal it by sort of analyzing what they've learned. So
it is—but some say it means they used it to פסקן pasken,
*pasken* to other people. Okay, but anyway, so a couple versions, they
that were revealed a מסכתא *masechta*, נתקיימה תורתם בידם *niskayma Toratam b'yadam*,
it was established. בני גליל Bnei Galil? דלא גלו מסכתא *Bnei Galil
delo galu masechta*, לא נתקיימה תורתם בידם *lo niskayma Toratam b'yadam*. Now
I should say the explanation of רש"י *Rashi* that גלו מסכתא *galu
masechta* means you got into it and analyzed it would be a
nice counterpart to the point before. Before the point was what makes
you remember it is very focused on learning the material, be very
precise of the language, learn from one source and so on. Now
it's saying part of what makes you remember is if you get
into it and analyze it and think about it, that also makes
you remember, it's not just about memorization, memorization is tied into understanding.
דוד David. גלי מסכתא *David gali masechta*, דוד *David* revealed a מסכת
*masechet*, again, whatever that means. שאול לא גלי מסכתא *Shaul lo gali
masechta*. דוד דגלי מסכתא כתיב ביה *David degali masechta kesiv beih*, so
by דוד *David* it says: יראיך יראוני וישמחו *Yereiecha yiruni veyismachu*, those
who fear you will see me and rejoice, because they know that
if they're asking me like a הלכה Halacha, *halachah* or פסק *psak*
or whatever, they're very happy because, you know, I know what I'm
talking about. Okay, and, you know, this ties into all those מדרשים
*Midrashim*, particularly in ברכות *Berachot* with דוד *David*, you know, sitting and,
you know, getting his hands bloody with—dealing with issues of miscarriage and
going to מפיבשת *Mephibosheth*. So everybody was very happy with him as
a פוסק *posek*. שאול דלא גלי מסכתא כתיב ביה *Shaul delo gali
masechta kesiv beih*: ובכל אשר יפנה ירשיע *uv'chol asher yifneh yarshia*, wherever
he would turn, he would do evil. So here it's not saying
like literally evil, like he was a bad person, but it means
that he would cause bad things to happen because presumably he would
פסקן
*pasken*
incorrectly. And not to end with such a negative statement about שאול
*Shaul*, actually already this is I think toning down the simple sense
of the פסוק *pasuk* because now his whole evil is just that
he didn't have a good enough understanding and פסקן *pasken*ed poorly, which
one thing it's saying how bad that is, but on the other
hand it's a little bit I think softening the judgment of שאול
*Shaul*. So consistent with that it says: אמר amar? רבי Rebbi, יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, מניין שמחל לו הקדוש ברוך הוא על אותו עוון
*Minayin shemachal lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu al oto avon*? How do you
know God forgave שאול *Shaul* for that sin? That sin meaning the
big sin, wiping out נוב עיר כהנים *Nov Ir Kohanim*. שנאמר *She'ne'emar*,
because of the פסוק
*pasuk* says that שמואל *Shmuel* says to שאול *Shaul*, right, when he
was raised from the dead, מחר אתה ובניך עמי *Machar atah u'vanecha
imi*. Tomorrow you and your son will be with me, they're going
to die in battle, right, people remember that story. So עמי *imi*
means with me במחיצתי *bimchitzati*, you'll be in my מחיצה *mechitzah*, meaning
you'll be in my chamber. So up in שמים *Shamayim*. So basically
you'll get עולם הבא *Olam HaBa*, you'll be right there with me,
you know, in my עולם הבא *Olam HaBa*. Okay, so that was
a little bit of a digression. Anyway, the point being, so we
have the difference between יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* and גליל Galil *Galil*, we
still don't know why it's relevant. So now we're going to find
out why it's relevant. אמר amar, רבי אבא *Amar Rabbi Abba*: אי
איכא דמשיילי להו לבני יהודה דדייקי לישנא *Ei ika demashyeili lehu l'vnei
Yehuda d'dayki lishna*, if there's somebody here that can ask the בני
יהודה *Bnei Yehuda*, people from Judea, because they're very precise with their
language, so you should ask them, מאברין תנן או o מעברין תנן?
ma'avrin tnan? Is it with an אלף aleph or is it with
an עין? ayin? Because they know what they're talking about. אחוזו תנן,
achuzu tnan, oh by the way, I also think, well let me
show you the other one. אחוזו תנן achuzu tnan או o אחוזו
תנן? achuzu tnan? There's a משנה Mishna about מומים mumim by a
בכור bechor and it speaks about like if it might be missing
a testicle and how you test for it, and speaks about the
animal sitting on its haunches, on its, you know, on its rear
end, so, buttocks. So that either אחוזו achuzu with an אלף aleph
or אחוזו achuzu with an עין. ayin. So if you, so yes,
they'll know it, so you should ask them. If somebody's going to
ask them, you should ask them because they'll know. Now here by
the way, if memory serves correctly, which it hasn't been so far
this morning, but okay, if memory serves correctly, יהודה was more, you
know,
was more, גליל Galil, was, was
had, was more cosmopolitan, more cities, more influenced I think by, you
know, by Hellenism and so on, whereas יהודה was more rural. Is
that correct Charlie? I saw you nodding. So actually going back to
the point I said before, in גליל, Galil. they were not דייק
לישני dayak lishna because the whole guttural issues was being lost and
being confused, like the guttural עין'ס ayins and so on. And you
notice that both of these questions were an אלף aleph or an
עין ayin question. So it said ask בני יהודה, they'll know the
difference between an אלף aleph and an עין. ayin. So, what? Ask
a תימני. Teimani. Ask a תימני, Teimani, exactly. So that was the
point, so I think that is part of this issue of דייק
לישני dayak lishna that their language remains more precise, and you know,
when it was becoming an amalgam, you know, pronunciations up in גליל.
So okay, so ask them. So the גמרא says, שיילונהו, shailunhu, so
they asked them. ואמרו להו, va'amru lehu, and they said back to
whoever asked, איכא דתני מעברין ואיכא דתני מאברין. ika de tanni ma'avrin
ve ika de tanni ma'abrin. There are two different versions. איכא דתני
אחוזו
ואיכא דתני אחוזו. ika de tanni achuzu ve ika de tanni achuzu.
Okay, fine. בני יהודה דייק לישני מאי? Bnei Yehuda dayak lishna mai?
Now what's an example of them דייק לישני? dayak lishna? So I've
been talking about the עין אלף, ayin aleph, the גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to give another example. דהוא בר יהודה דאמר להו, dehu bar Yehuda
de'amar lehu, there was a certain person from Judea that was saying
to people, טלית יש לי למכור. talit yesh li limkor. I have
a טלית talit to sell. אמרו ליה, amru lei, מאי גוון טליתך?
mai gavan talitecha? What color is it? אמר להו, amar lehu, כתרדין
עלי אדמה, ketardin alei adama, like the, like beets, the leaves of
beets that grow from the ground. So it's a particular shade of
green, not the beets themselves, the leaves. Now why, what is the
point that ah look how precise he was? So you know, well
because he gave you a very precise hue. But the מהרש"א Maharsha
says a better point. The מהרש"א Maharsha says because he, normally how
would you say green in Hebrew? ירוק. yarok. The problem is if
you look in the משנה, Mishna, ירוק yarok sometimes means green and
sometimes means yellow. It's like a green-yellow continuum. So he says he
didn't want to say ירוק yarok because you wouldn't know if he
meant green or yellow. So he said like the leaves of this
beet. Okay, he was very careful. בני גליל דלא דייק לישני מאי?
Bnei Galil de lo dayak lishna mai? What about בני גליל? דהוא
בר גלילא דהוה קאזיל, dehu bar Galila dehavah ka'azil, there was a
person from Galilee that was going. ואמר להו, ve'amar lehu, אמר למאן
אמר למאן? amar leman amar leman? Who has אמר, amar who has
אמר? amar, Now the מהרש"א Maharsha clearly says the גרסה girsa is
חמר למאן אמר למאן chamar leman amar leman because you'll see the
גמרא comes up with four possibilities about what this means. אמרו ליה,
amru lei, so they said to him, גלילא שוטה, Galila shota, stupid
Galilean, what are you asking for? חמור למירכב? chamor lemirkav? Are you
asking about a חמור, chamor, a donkey to ride on? או חמר
למשתי? o chamar limishti? Or you're asking for wine to drink? So
that's the first אמר, which is why the מהרש"א Maharsha says the
first אמר was actually חמר. chamar. Okay. Now the second one, what
are you asking about? עמר למילבש? amar lemilbash? Are you asking about
wool to get dressed with? או אימר לאיכסא? o imar le'iksa? Or
you're asking for an אימר, imar, a sheep to שחט? shacht? What
are you asking? Now by the way notice all of this is
about אלף, aleph, עין, ayin, and חת. chet. So that whole idea
that this is a question about the guttural language letters could you
know very well plays out here. So, ההוא איתתא, hahu itata, now
another story, there was a woman דבעיה למימר לחבירתה, deba'ya lemimar lechaverta,
this is just talking about people that speak in a sloppy way
and again, you know, might be referring to Galileans, which have a
more of an amalgam in terms of what's happening to their language.
So she wanted to say to her friend, תא דאוכליך חלבא, ta
de'ochlich chalba, come let me feed you milk. אמר לה, amar la,
she said, שלוחתי, shiluchti, which is a mispronunciation of like my friend,
my neighbor, which the actual correct word is רש"י says, where is
it?
She wanted to say שלובתי, shaluvti, which is a way of saying
my like you know my friend. So and she and she said
שלוחתי, shiluchti, so already she's making a mistake. And then she said,
where am
I? Yeah,
תוכליך לביא. tochlich lavi. So she wanted to say דאוכליך חלבא de'ochlich
chalba and she said תוכליך לביא, tochlich lavi, which means a lion
should eat you. Okay. What? Like
Freudian slip. Exactly.
Okay,
also notice yeah again I would still right point out... Also notice
again I would still point out this whole חית Chet issue is
going on here. ההיא איתתא דאתיא לקמיה דדיינא. Hahi iteta de'asya lekamei
dedayana. So a certain woman came in front of a judge. אמרה
ליה, Amrah lei, she said to him: מארי קירי, Mari kiri, so
she said, Mr. Slave, because she wanted to say קירי kiri with
a קוף kuf which is a way of referring to like an
honorific, like you know like Lord, but she said קירי kiri with
a כף chaf which is slave. תיפלה הוות לי, Tifla havat li,
so she said, I had, she wanted to say טבלה tavla like
a tableau, but she said תיפלה tifla which is like a beam
I had, וגנובך מין vigenovach min and she wanted to say it
was stolen from me, but she said וגנובך מין vigenovach min means
that they stole you, the judge. Okay. וקדו הוות Vekadu havat and
this was how it was. Okay, כדו kadu means now but she
really wanted to say וכדן, vechadan, it was like this, this is
how it was. דכד שדיי לכו עילויה, Dechad shadyei lechu ilveia, if
they would stretch you on this tableau, לא מטו כרעיך ארעא. lo
matu kara'ich ara. Your legs wouldn't reach the ground. Now the last
part was not a mispronunciation, it was just being like very rude
and inappropriate, sort of giving an image of a judge being stretched
out on a tableau. Okay, but clearly she is having all these
like right mispronunciations. אמתא דבי רבי, Amata devei Rabbi, now we're starting
to have more positive versions about good use of language. And the
female servant or slave of Rabbi, כי הוות משתעיא בלשון חכמה, ki
havat mishtaya bileshon chachma, when she wanted to talk in a wise
way, we'll see what it means. It sort of means like you
know not be sort of vulgar or you know be sort of
subtle. אמרה הכי, Amrah hachi, she said this. עלת נקפסט בחד, Alat
nakfast bechad, the what's it called the ladle I guess, whatever,
went into, you know, banged into the barrel. Meaning the ladle that
you use to draw the wine from the barrel, it's banging at
the bottom of the barrel, meaning there's no wine left. ידו נשרא
לקיניהון, Yadu nishra leki'neihon, let the eagles fly to their nest. Meaning
there's no wine left, it's time for all the פחמיא pachmaya to
go home. Okay. So, but what is a maid doing telling me
it's time to go home? So therefore she spoke in a more
you know roundabout and respectful way, in a more metaphorical way. וכי
בעת דלינסבון, Vechi ba'as delinsavon, now when she wanted the students to
or the visitors to
stay, הוות אמרה להו: havat amrah lehu: יעדי בתר חברתא, ya'adi batar
chaverta, let it be removed from its friend, which means the plug
of the wine barrel should be removed from the barrel. ותשקופי
עלת בכד vetishkufi alat bekad and let the ladle float in the
barrel, there's so much wine it'll float on the top. כאיפא דאזלא
בימא ke'ifa de'azla beyama like a ship that sails in the sea.
Okay, so again it's just a nice way of talking that says
that sort of is inviting everybody to stay
even though it wasn't like her place to invite people, but she
so therefore she spoke about it you know she alluded to it
in this way. It's polite, you know it's a polite language. רבי
יוסי בר אסיאן, Rabbi Yossi bar Asyan, now Rabbi Yossi bar Asyan,
כי
הוה משתעי בלשון חכמה, ki hava mishtayei bileshon chachma, when he wanted
to speak in this sort of like you know wise way, in
a language of you know sort of this
more indirect way, אמר, he said like this: עשו לי שור במשפט,
asu li shor bemishpat, make for me an ox in judgment, בטור
מסכן betur misken in an unfortunate mountain. Now what the heck does
that mean? So this is more like a riddle. Okay, and שור
במשפט shor bemishpat if you translate that to Aramaic, תור דין, tor
din, תורדן, tordan, תרדין tardin is beets. Okay, בטור מסכן betur misken
in a poor mountain, so it's הר דל, har dal, which is
חרדל. chardal. So I would like some beets with mustard. Okay, now
we're getting into riddles. וכי הוה שאל באושפיזא, Vechi hava she'el be'ushpiza,
when he wanted to know about an innkeeper, אמר הכי amar hachi
he would say
this: גבר פום דין חי, Gvar pum din chai,
this man's mouth or the man mouth judgment live. What does that
mean? So גבר gvar is איש, ish, פום pum is
פה, peh, אושפיז, ushpiz, דין din is זה zeh and חי chai
is נא. na. So אושפיזכנא. ushpizachna. So anyway, little riddle. Okay. Now
the Gemara says: מה זאת טובה יש, Mah zos tovah yesh, so
you know what
you know what's his welfare? How's he doing? רבי אבהו כי הוה
משתעי בלשון חכמה, Rabbi Abbahu ki hava mishtayei bileshon chachma, when Rabbi
Abbahu wanted to speak in this more riddle language, הוה אמר הכי
hava amar hachi he would say this: אסריגו לפחמים, asrigu lepachamim, turn
the coals into אתרוגים, esrogim, which basically means make them like you
know yellow or Rashi says red, I don't know too many red
אתרוגים, esrogim, but anyway fire up the coals. ארקיעו לזהבים, arkiu lezehavim,
spread out the gold because you know now they're yellowish or reddish
yellow so make you know spread out the coals. ועשו לי שני
מגידי בעלטה ve'asu li shney magidei ba'alata and make for me two
speakers in the night. Who are speakers in the night? So they're
like the roosters that crow as the night is ending. איכא דאמרי
Ika d'amri some say ויעשו לי בהן שני מגידי בעלטה. veyasu li
bahen shne meguidei be'alata. I don't really understand the big difference between
those. Make me with them. Okay. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבי אבהו. Amru
leih Rabbanan l'Rabbi Abahu. So now another little play on words we're
going to get to. The rabbis said to Rabbi Abahu, הצפיננו hatspinenu
show us, right, צופה tsofe is to look, היכן רבי אלעאי צפון.
heichan Rabbi Elai tsafun. So again, the play הצפיננו hatspinenu צפון. tsafun.
Where is he hiding? Okay, so they were looking for Rabbi Elai
but they were sort of having fun with the way they were
talking, doing little word games. Somebody once said that this is what
they did before they had TV. Okay. So אמר להו Amar lehu
he said to them,
עלץ בנערה alats bena'arah he rejoiced in a young woman, אהרונית aharonit
an Aaronite woman from אהרן, Aharon,
אחרונית acharonit last, עירנית iranit like wise or lively, והנהרתהו vehinehartehu and
it kept him awake. So obviously there's a play here: אהרונית
אחרונית אהרונית אחרונית עירנית והנהרתהו. aharonit acharonit aharonit acharonit iranit vehinehartehu. So
what does this mean? אמרי ליה אישה amrei leih ishah which would
seem a little crude, okay, that it meant that he was spending
time at night with his wife and he stayed up pretty late.
So what's אהרונית? aharonit? So רש"י says that she's a בת כהן,
bas kohen, אחרונית acharonit a last wife, maybe it's a second wife,
עירנית iranit and she was very pretty or lively, and he stayed
up late at night being with his wife. ואיכא דאמרי ליה מסכתא
Ve'ika d'amrei leih masechta and some say it was more of a
metaphor. It doesn't literally mean his wife, it means a, and that's
a whole other metaphor that goes on about like תורה Torah as
the other woman and this whole sort of type of romantic even
sexual relationship and so on. So he spent last night studying, learning
all night, he was very involved in a lively מסכתא. Okay, so
where were we?
Wasn't Rabbi Elai the father of Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi they're talking about?
I
don't think so.
Isn't he Rabbi Yehuda?
I think this is Rabbi Elai the אמורא, Amora, I don't know,
pretty sure this is an אמורא. Amora. Okay, so now the גמרא
said, אמרו ליה לרבי אלעאי, amru leih l'Rabbi Elai, right, you'll see
right now it's the same Rabbi Elai, now they asked Rabbi Elai,
הצפיננו היכן רבי אבהו צפון. hatspinenu heichan Rabbi Abahu tsafun. Tell us
where's Rabbi Abahu hidden? Okay, so notice, first they asked Rabbi Abahu
where's Rabbi Elai, then they asked Rabbi Elai where's Rabbi Abahu. So
obviously they were playing some type of a
game, okay. So give us a little riddle essentially what it was.
Okay, so here's what he said back to them: אמר להן Amar
lahen נתייעץ במכתיר, nisya'etz bemachtir, he took counsel from the one who
gives the crown, meaning the נשיא. Nasi. He was, so it means
that he was given סמיכה semicha because he was given authority to
פסקן, והנגיב למפיבושת, vehenguiv l'Mefivoshet, and he went south to Mephibosheth, meaning
he went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to learn תורה because מפיבושת
Mefivoshet is they sort of held up as the רבי of דוד.
So I have to tell you, this answer was not as clever
as the previous one. Okay. So Rabbi Abahu knew how to play
the game
better. Okay, anyway, אמר רבי יהושע
בן חנניה Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya מימיי לא נצחני אדם חוץ
מאישה תינוק ותינוקת, miyamai lo nitsachani adam chutz me'ishah tinok v'tinoket, very
famous little
מדרש. Midrash. Nobody ever bested me
except for a woman, a young boy, and a young girl. Doesn't
literally mean an infant. אישה מאי Ishah mai what was the story
with a woman? פעם אחת נתארחתי אצל אכסניא אחת, Paam achat nis'arachti
etsel achsanya achat, once I spent time by a certain innkeeper, a
woman. עשתה לי פולין ביום ראשון astah li pulin beyom rishon she
made for me like lentils on the first day. אכלתים ולא שיירתי
מהם כלום achaltim velo shayarti mehem klum I ate them and I
completely finished them. They were delicious. שנייה shniya the second day, same
thing, ולא שיירתי מהם כלום velo shayarti mehem klum I cleaned my
plate. ביום שלישי Beyom shlishi on the third day, הקדיחתן במלח hikdichtan
bamelach she added too much salt to it and it was spoiled.
כיוון שטעמתי keivan shetaamti when I tasted it, משכתי ידי מהם mashachti
yadai mehem I left it aside, I didn't eat. אמרה לי Amrah
li she said to me, רבי מפני מה אין אתה סועד Rebbi
mipne mah ein attah so'ed why are you not eating? אמרתי לה
Amarti lah כבר סעדתי מבעוד יום kvar saadeti mibe'od yom I ate
something already before. אמרה לי Amrah li she said to me, היה
לך למשוך ידך מן הפת hayah lecha limshoch yadcha min hapas if
you really weren't hungry then you shouldn't have had the bread and
you should have filled yourself up with the main meal. So that's
not a good explanation. If you really weren't hungry, you wouldn't have
eaten the bread. You would have saved your appetite for the beans.
So she said, I'm going to tell you what it is, I
know you're not eating it, this is the subtext, because I added
too much salt. But let me tell you why I did that.
I wanted to make a
point. אמרה לי Amrah li she said, רבי שמא לא הנחת פאה
בראשונים Rebbi shema lo hinachta pe'ah barishonim maybe you didn't leave over
פאה, pe'ah, right, a corner, you didn't leave a little food over
because you wiped your plate clean. Apparently they had a מנהג, minhag,
it's very interesting they call it פאה, pe'ah, the use of these
biblical and cultural things in contemporary scenarios like the idea of מעשר
כספים. ma'aser kesafim. So here they had an idea of פאה. pe'ah.
You don't clean off your whole plate, you leave a little over.
And רש"י says so that the servant who's cleaning the plate can
eat from what's left over. Okay, so same idea like leaving over.
over for the poor. What? שיריים. Shirayim. Yes, so maybe you didn't
leave over פאה בראשונים Pe'ah barishonim
וכל כך אמרו חכמים vechol kach amru chachomim but haven't the sages
said אין משיירין פאה באילפס, Ein meshayrin Pe'ah b'ilpas, you don't leave
over it in the pot when you serve from the pots to
the plates, אבל משיירין פאה בקערה, aval meshayrin Pe'ah bakara, you leave
it over on the plate. So I basically wanted to, so he
did this essentially to make him aware that he shouldn't have been
eating every single all up. Okay, תינוקת מאי, Tinokes mai, what's the
story about the young girl?
She taught him הלכה, she taught him a lesson, at least at
least in terms of basic דרך ארץ. Derech Eretz. פעם אחת הייתי
מהלך בדרך, Pa'am achas hayiti mehalech baderech, I was going on the
way, והיתה דרך עוברת בשדה, ve'aysa derech overes basadeh, and there was
a path going through a field, והייתי מהלך בה, vehayiti mehalech bah,
and I would walk on it. אמרה לי תינוקת אחת, Amra li
tinokes achas, so a certain young girl said to me, רבי, לא
שדה היא זו, lo sadeh hi zo, isn't this a field? A
field is a place where as opposed to a בקעה, bika, valley,
where you plant things. What are you doing walking through somebody's field?
אמרתי לה, Amarti lah, and I said to her, אמרתי לה, amarti
lah, לא דרך כבושה היא, lo derech k'vusha hi, what do you
mean? There's a path here. אמרה לי, Amra li, she said back
to me, לסטים כמותך כבשוה, Listim k'moscha k'vashuha, yeah, robbers like you
turned it into a path like because everybody thinks they can walk
on it they made it into a path. I gotta tell you
this is so true, you know, right now if you think about
the shortcut here to the שול, shul, right, it's because people were
walking through and made it a path so now they laid a
sidewalk there, but actually it's a process and when you're participating in
it you could still be, you know, going where you should not
be going and everybody thinks it's okay because somebody else did it.
Okay, the last one is תינוק מאי, tinok mai, a young boy,
what's the story? פעם אחת הייתי מהלך בדרך וראיתי תינוק יושב על
פרשת דרכים, Pa'am achas hayiti mehalech baderech ve'ra'isi tinok yoshev al parashas
drachim, I saw a young boy sitting by a crossroads. And you
know what Yogi Berra says, when you come to a crossroads, take
it. Okay, ואמרתי לו, ve'amarti lo, I said to him, באיזה דרך
נלך לעיר, be'eizeh derech nelech la'ir, actually a fork in the road,
anyway, which way do I get to the city? אמר לי, Amar
li, he said to me, זו קצרה וארוכה, zo ktzara va'arucha, this
one is short and long, וזו, vezo, and this one is ארוכה
וקצרה, arucha u'ktzara, long and short. So הלכתי בקצרה וארוכה, halachti b'ktzara
va'arucha, I went with the one he said was short and long.
כיון שהגעתי לעיר, keivan she'higati la'ir, I got to the city, ומצאתי
שמקיפין אותה גנות ופרדסים, umatzati she'makifin osa ganos u'pardesim, the you know,
yes, it got me right to the outside of the city, but
there were all these gardens and you know and whatever,
orchards, so it took me forever to get around all of that
into the city. חזרתי לאחורי, Chazarti l'achorai, I turned around and I
went back to him, אמרתי לו, amarti lo, and I said, בני
הלא אמרת לי קצרה, bni halo amarta li ktzara, you told me
it was short. אמר לי, Amar li, ולא אמרתי לך ארוכה, velo
amarti lach arucha, but I told you it was a short one
that in the end will prove to be long. נשקתי על ראשו,
Nashakti al rosho, I kissed him on his head, ואמרתי לו, ve'amarti
lo, and I said to him, אשריכם ישראל, ashreichum Yisrael, praise be
you Israel, שכולכם חכמים גדולים אתם מגדולכם ועד קטנכם, she'kulchem chachamim gedolim
atem migdolchem ve'ad k'tanchem, and men and women. Okay, very nice end,
that whole idea of ארוכה שהיא קצרה, arucha she'hi ktzara, קצרה שהיא
ארוכה ktzara she'hi arucha is a nice metaphor that's used elsewhere. Alright,
יישר כח, Yasher koach, יישר כח Yasher koach to all of you.